now that we have seen how pipelines work
and how they are affected by hazards and
dependencies let's talk about how many
stages a pipeline should have in the
pipelines we have seen so far the ideal
CPI is one we will later in this course
see pipelines where the ideal CPI will
be larger than one because they try to
do more than one instruction per cycle
but regardless there is some ideal CPI
that the pipeline should be achieving
and it boils down to executing some
number of instructions every single
cycle now let's consider what happens
when we add more stages to the pipeline
we get more hazards this way we have
already seen that some of the
dependencies cause the number of stalls
or flush cycles that depend on how deep
the pipeline is for example if a branch
is resolved in the second or third stage
of the pipeline we only have to flush
one or two instructions that we have
incorrectly fetched if the pipeline
however resolves branches in something
like 15 cycle
then we will flush 14 instructions when
we have a branch that we incorrectly
resolved so we have more hazards when we
have more stages and what that does is
it adds more of that CPI penalty so the
CPI
increases because of that penalty that
we have when we have a hazard but with
more stages there is less work per stage
which means that our cycle time can be
decreased less work per stage means that
every cycle that is less work to do
which means we can do it in less time so
we can speed up our clock we already
know the iron law which says that the
execution time is equal to the number of
instructions times the CPI times the
cycle time if we have the same number of
instructions because we're just trying
to figure out for the same instruction
set whether we should have a processor
that has more or fewer stages if we
increase the number of stages our CPI
goes up which increases execution time
but the cycle time drops
which decreases execution time so the
number of stages needs to be chosen in a
way that balances the CPI and the cycle
time you don't want to have too few
stages because then your cycle time will
be too long but you don't want to have
too many stages because then your CPI
will be too high we can plot the number
of stages here and how execution time
depends on it and this is what it looks
like as you increase the number of
stages the execution time drops because
you still don't have too many
hazards but you're improving the clock
cycle time at some point you get fewer
benefits from reducing the cycle time
and the CPI increase starts to hurt
Beyond some point you are no longer
shortening the cycle time very much but
you're suffering a lot from hazards that
are now causing dependencies that cause
many many cycles of stores or flushes so
the bottom of this curve for modern
processors would be at some something
like 30 to 40 stages which would be a
very very deep pipeline so this is if
you only consider performance so for
performance we want a pipeline that is
30 to 40 stages deep but we need to
consider power if we add more stages we
are shortening the cycle time so we have
more cycles per second and in each of
those Cycles we now have more pipeline
latches that spend energy latching
temporary results so power quickly
increased es with the number of stages
if we plot power it does something like
this so because of performance and power
considerations we want to choose
something that is not in this
performance optimal point we want
something that is also power efficient
so we end up with 10 to 15 stages in
modern processors so again this is not
because performance is best when you
have this many stages it's because it's
the number of stages that balances
pretty good performance with relatively
low power consumption or at least
manageable power consumption